Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ל"ג Lamed Gimmel
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 33, we're a little bit behind but we
are going to catch up today and we begin on ל"ב עמוד
ב' Lamed Bet Amud Bet about 20 lines down, we're starting with
תדע, Teda, the first word on the line is משאו. Masa'o.
And our learning should be in the זכות zchus of the חיילים
Chayalim and the protection and safety of the חיילים Chayalim and חיילות
Chayalot and the swift return of the hostages and speedy end of
the war. Okay, so we're in the middle of a discussion of
whether צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim is דאורייתא. De'oraita. In another
גמרא, Gemara, the issue of צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim
De'oraita means how much is that a principle that obligates a certain
type of behavior or permits behavior to violate a דרבנן Derabbanan to
save your animal in pain on שבת. Shabbat. Here the גמרא Gemara
is framing it in the sense of is it a תורה Torah
value so that we can see that it impacts certain types of
halachic calculuses about like, you know, unloading even for free, loading up
with a fee, פריקה בחינם, Prika Bechinam, טעינה בשכר, Te'inah Bishchar,
or how whether you interpret the verse about משאו, Masa'o, משאו הראוי
לו, Masa'o Hara'uy Lo, different if it's a value, then you'll interpret
the פסוקים psukim accordingly, which is important because it shows us that
sometimes an understanding of what the values are influence the דרשות drashot
of the פסוקים, psukim, it's not all just a mechanical דרשה. drasha.
So now we're going to continue with arguing both directions. Let's take
a look. תדע, Teda, says the גמרא, Gemara, דצער בעלי חיים לאו
דאורייתא, d'Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim Lav De'oraita, I'll prove to you, you should
know that it's not from the, it's not a תורה Torah principle.
דתני רישא, d'tani reisha, הלך וישב לו ואמר לו הוי עליך מצוה
לפרוק פרוק פטור שנאמר עמו, halach veyashav lo ve'amar lo hovei alecha
mitzvah lifrok perok, patur shene'emar imo,
because the beginning of the, you know, the ברייתא Braita says that
if the owner goes and sits down and says, hey, you know,
you've got a
מצוה mitzvah to do it, so I'm going to sit and watch
you do it and you go ahead and do it, then it
says that you're exempt because it says עזוב תעזוב עמו, azov ta'azov
imo, with him. Actually, I'm sorry, that's the משנה, Mishna, not the
ברייתא. Braita. Okay, so the משנה Mishna says that. So that shows
so ואי סלקא דעתך צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא, v'is salka daitach Tza'ar
Ba'alei Chayim De'oraita,
but okay, now it's the issue about unloading the animal, the animal
is suffering. So even though the owner is being completely irresponsible and
taking advantage of you and so on, you still have a suffering
animal here. So ואי סלקא דעתך צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא, v'is salka
daitach Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim De'oraita, מה לי איתיה למריה בהדיה ומה לי
ליתיה למריה בהדיה, mai li itai le'marei bahadei umai li leika le'marei
bahadei, what do I care if the owner is helping or not
helping?
He doesn't deserve to be helped, but לעולם צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא,
le'olam Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim De'oraita, if צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim
is a תורה Torah principle and what's implicit here is that is
what is the operative or an piece of what is operative in
terms of the obligation of פריקה וטעינה, Prika v'Te'inah, because is פריקה
וטעינה Prika v'Te'inah about helping the owner not losing his property, not
letting him
be stranded on the side of the road, or is it at
least part of it about helping the animal? That's the question of
צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא. Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim De'oraita. So if צער בעלי
חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim is דאורייתא, De'oraita, says the גמרא, Gemara, how
could you not help him when he's just, how could you not
care about the animal? Who cares even if the owner is acting
in this way and just sitting and not helping you. So the
גמרא Gemara let's hear how it responds, very good question. The גמרא
Gemara says, מי סברת פטור פטור לגמרי ודלמא פטור בחינם וחייב בשכר?
mi savrat patur patur legamrei v'dilma patur bechinam vechayav besachar? The גמרא
Gemara says no, it doesn't mean you're exempt, it means that you
don't have to do it for free, you can get paid. All
right, you have to take care of the animal because the animal
suffers, but now you don't have to but you can get reimbursed
for your effort because the owner is being irresponsible and taking advantage.
All right, so it's not the פשט pshat of the משנה Mishna
but that's what the גמרא Gemara says. והכי קאמר רחמנא, v'hachi ka'amar
Rachmana, and here's how you could read the משנה. Mishna. והכי קאמר
רחמנא איתיה למריה בהדיה עביד גביה בחינם, v'hachi ka'amar Rachmana itai le'marei
bahadei avid gabei bechinam, when the master is helping you, then you
help for free. Then, you know, he's in trouble, he's doing his
responsibility, so you help out for free. וכי ליתיה למריה בהדיה עביד
גביה בשכר, v'chi leika le'marei bahadei avid gabei besachar, and if the
owner is being irresponsible and he's not there,
then you help out the poor suffering animal and you get paid
back for it, but you still have to help the animal. ולעולם
צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא, u'le'olam Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim De'oraita, and I could
still claim that צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim is a תורה
Torah principle and it is part of what is operative here. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara has a סימן, Siman, a way to remember
the next set of proofs, you know, they would do these things
for the sake of because it was all oral to remember how
the proofs were stacked up. לימא מסייעא ליה, Lemma Mesaye'a lei, let's
try to prove this principle now that צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei
Chayim is from the תורה. Torah. בהמת עובד כוכבים מטפל בה כבהמת
ישראל. Behemat Oveid Kochavim metapel bah kebehemat Yisrael. Okay,
if the animal is owned by a non-Jew, then you still have
to take care of it as much as you would take care
of it being owned by a Jew. So that seems like, you
know, all of these obligations, צדקה tzedakah type of obligations, extending yourself
for your neighbor, we know in general חז"ל Chazal interpret them to
be fundamentally between Jews. You know, there's none of the, so obviously
there's a question about like harming non-Jews, but in terms of these
brotherly obligations, obligations extending yourself, that's only between Jews. So if the
idea of פריקה וטעינה Prika v'Te'inah were to help the owner, you
know, loss of property, stranded, abandoned, whatever, then we understand
that it would not apply to a non-Jew. But if it is
because of the suffering of an animal, so then it makes sense
that it should apply to a non-Jew. So here if it says
that you take care of the animal of non-Jew the same way
of a Jew, that's really is a pretty good proof that the
operative principle here is the צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. Okay?
So בהמת עכו"ם מטפל בה כבהמת ישראל. behemat akum metapel bah k'vehemat
yisrael. אי אמרת בשלמא ee amarta bishlama צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא, tza'ar
ba'alei chayim d'ora'ita, if צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is a
Torah principle, משום הכי מטפל בה כבהמת ישראל, mishum hachi metapel bah
k'vehemat yisrael, then okay, then it doesn't make a difference who owns
it, the concern is the animal. אלא אי אמרת צער בעלי חיים
לאו דאורייתא, ela ee amarta tza'ar ba'alei chayim lav d'ora'ita, but if
צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim isn't a Torah principle, אמאי מטפל
בה כבהמת ישראל, amai metapel bah k'vehemat yisrael, why should you take
care of it? התם משום איבה. hatam mishum eivah. No, that's not
a real עיקר דין, ikar din, that's not really the mitzvah of
פריקה וטעינה, prika uteina, that is so the non-Jews should not be
have enmity towards us. We do these types of acts if you
leave them and abandon and you don't help that engenders tremendous איבה,
eivah, but it's not an actual obligation of פריקה וטעינה. prika uteina.
And the Gemara says הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistavra, you know
that actually makes sense that that's more the right explanation here, דתני
detani because then the Braitah goes on to say אם היתה טעונה
יין אסור אין זקוק לה. im hayta te'una yayin assur ein zakuk
lah. If the animal was carrying like יין נסך, yayin nesech, wine
of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, then you don't help him out. All
right, now, אי אמרת בשלמא לאו דאורייתא, ee amarta bishlama lav d'ora'ita,
if the principle here of helping the non-Jew's animal is not because
of a concern of צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim, it's only
because of איבה, eivah, now then you can distinguish when he's carrying
wine and not carrying wine. משום הכי אין זקוק לה. mishum hachi
ein zakuk lah. That then you can say, you know, you don't
have to help him because you could say look, you know, I'd
love to help you but this wine is עבודה זרה avoda zara
wine, it's forbidden to us, and the Gemara in other places thinks
that non-Jews will understand those types of religious concerns. So it all
makes perfect sense if it's if צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim
is not the operative principle and if איבה eivah is the operative
principle. אלא אי אמרת דאורייתא, ela ee amarta d'ora'ita, but if צער
בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is דאורייתא d'ora'ita and that's the operative
principle and why you help the animal of a non-Jew, אמאי אין
זקוק לה, amai ein zakuk lah, why should you not have to
help it? Of course you'd have to help, who cares that it's
יין אסור? yayin assur? The poor animal is suffering. So the Gemara
says, no, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's how you could read the
Braitah: ולטעינה יין אסור אין זקוק לה. ult'eina yayin assur ein zakuk
lah.
To reload it, you're obligated to unload the animal even of a
non-Jew, that's the mitzvah of פריקה, prika, that's the mitzvah of צער
בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim.
After it's unloaded, to reload it, that's not about צער בעלי חיים,
tza'ar ba'alei chayim, that's about helping the other person. So the reloading,
that you would do if, you know, for איבה, eivah, but you
wouldn't do it if it was יין של איסור. yayin shel issur.
But the unloading, then it doesn't matter what the animal's carrying, of
course you would unload, the principle being צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei
chayim. Okay, so the fact that you help the animal of a
non-Jew on the face of it seems to prove that the concern
is the animal, but it might really all be about איבה. eivah.
Let's keep on going. תא שמע, ta shema, come in here. בהמת
עובד כוכבים ומשאוי ישראל. behemat oved kochavim umasoy yisrael. If the animal
is owned by the non-Jew and the, you know, the burden that
it's carrying, the wares are owned by a Jew. So this also
is a good question: if פריקה וטעינה prika uteina even if it's
not about צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim,
what is it about? Is it about the owner being in danger?
רמב"ם rambam categorizes it under the mitzvah of, you know,
שמירת נפש, shmirat nefesh, that, you know, you're somebody's abandoned by the
roadside. Is it about the property being damaged or lost, and what
property, the animal or the load that it's carrying? Right, so here
it says that if it is the animal of a non-Jew and
the load is the wares are owned by a Jew, וחדלת. vechadata.
So the pasuk says, you know, the pasuk is וחדלת vechadata in
a rhetorical sense: do you think you should hold yourself back? No,
of course you should help. But the Gemara reads it sometimes, you
know, like there's a mitzvah to be, like it says by an
אבידה, aveida, sometimes it's a mitzvah להתעלם. lehit'alem. So here too, וחדלת,
vechadata, sometimes you shouldn't help. All right, so it's saying that if
it's a non-Jew animal and a Jewish burden, don't help. So why
how could you not be helping an animal if it's about צער
בעלי חיים? tza'ar ba'alei chayim? And we'll have to anyway figure out
who cares about animal versus burden. But if but either way, how
could you not care about the animal if צער בעלי חיים tza'ar
ba'alei chayim is the operative principle? So let's see what the Gemara
says. ואי אמרת צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא
אמאי וחדלת? ve'ee amarta tza'ar ba'alei chayim d'ora'ita amai vechadata? If צער
בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is from the Torah, then how could
it say וחדלת? vechadata? How could you not help the animal? עזוב
תעזוב מיבעי ליה. azov ta'azov mibei lei. You should be reading the
pasuk that says you have to help because you have an animal
suffering here. So the Gemara says, לעולם צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא. leolam
tza'ar ba'alei chayim d'ora'ita. No, I'm going to claim צער בעלי חיים
tza'ar ba'alei chayim is from the Torah. התם בטעינה, hatam biteina, and
we're not talking about unloading like the answer we gave before, we're
talking about reloading, and that's the issue. And reloading is about helping
the person. Okay, so and somehow we'll see in a minute how
it's going to make sense why it matters who owns the donkey
and who owns the load. So let's see, the Gemara will spell
it out. אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's what it's about, reloading,
אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of the Braitah.
בהמת ישראל ומשאוי עובד כוכבים, behemat yisrael umasoy oved kochavim, if it's
the reverse, the animal was owned by a Jew and the load
the wares were by a non-Jew, עזוב תעזוב, azov ta'azov, then you
have to help. אי בטעינה, ee biteina, now if it's about loading
up, אמאי עזוב תעזוב, amai azov ta'azov, why should you help out?
Right, you know, why should you be helping him reload? If the,
if, so presumably it's the concern here is about the, about the,
about the burden. I mean why, you know, what does it make
sense about why you focus on the animal or do you focus
on the wares? This ברייתא braisa clearly says
that, that you focus on who owns the animal. But why does
that make sense if the issue is reloading? Maybe you should focus
on who owns the wares because you're helping the person get their
wares to the next city. How does any of this make sense?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So, והשתא דאמרת עזב תעזוב,
v'hashta d'amart azov ta'azov, משום צער דישראל? mishum tza'ar d'Yisrael? Because your
poor Jew is going to be in pain or whatever. It's funny,
צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim, צער דישראל. tza'ar d'Yisrael. Okay, because
you're leaving the Jew without helping him out. אי הכי אפילו רישא
נמי. ei hachi afilu reisha nami. So okay, what difference does it
make who owns the animal, who owns the wares? In one or
the other, there'll be a non-Jew that'll be losing out and a
Jew losing out. One will lose out the animal, one will lose
out the wares. What is the logic here of the distinction? So
the גמרא Gemara says no. רישא בחמור עובד כוכבים וסיפא בחמור ישראל.
Reisha b'chamor oved kochavim v'seifa b'chamor Yisrael. The first case,
when the donkey was owned by the non-Jew, the donkey driver was
non-Jewish. And in the second case, when the donkey was owned by
the Jew, the donkey driver was also Jewish. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי פסקת? mai paskat? What makes you, how are you able
to divide it that way? What makes you so sure? סתמא דמילתא
איניש בתר חמריה אזיל. Stama d'milsa inish basar chamrei azil. Okay, because
normally the person who owns the donkey is the one driving the
donkey, which is a reasonable explanation. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. In a case where—so what's bottom line it say? In
a case where the donkey is owned by one and the wares
are owned by another, each person has some potential loss of property.
But the גמרא Gemara is saying that the question of your obligation
of טעינה—it's teina reading this as being
טעינה—is teina a question of the person you're helping that's in front
of you, not if somebody's money maybe going at a little bit
of a risk. So if the person in front of you is
Jewish, which will be the case if the donkey is owned by
a Jew, then you help him to reload. If the person in
front of you is not Jewish, because the donkey is owned by
the non-Jew and the non-Jew is the one there, then you don't
help him reload. That's the calculus of reloading, who is the person
in front of you? But unloading, if צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei
chayim is דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, you would unload regardless in both cases. Okay,
so that's how the גמרא Gemara is explaining that. Let's keep on
going. Now actually I should just pause before going on. How would
this ברייתא braisa have made sense if צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei
chayim was not דאורייתא? d'Oraisa? If צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim
was not דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, we wouldn't worry about whether the owner was
there. We would focus on the idea that it was about unloading,
and the ברייתא braisa would tell us the question is: whose donkey
are you helping? If you're helping the Jew's donkey, you unload, because
the concern is not about the wares, the concern is about the
donkey. And if the donkey is being crushed under the load, donkey
is property, then you unload the donkey if the Jew owns it.
But if the non-Jew owns it, you don't bother unloading it because
you don't care about the loss of property. That's how the גמרא
Gemara would have explained it. But because to work with the principle
of צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא tza'ar ba'alei chayim d'Oraisa and we're talking
unloading you'll always do, and the question is loading up, we have
to make it about the presence of the Jew or of the
non-Jew. Okay, now let's—the גמרא Gemara is not done, though. Let's continue.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: והא וחדלת מעזוב לו, עזב
תעזוב בפריקה הוא דכתיב. V'ha v'chadalta m'azov lo, azov ta'azov b'prika hu
d'chtiv.
You can't say that that's פשט, pshat, that the פשט pshat here
about one being owned by a Jew and one by a non-Jew
is talking about the question of reloading it. The פסוקים pesukim being
quoted are the פסוקים pesukim about unloading. אמר ליה, Amar lei, okay,
so now we're stuck in a corner. Clearly because it's quoting פסוקים
pesukim of unloading, this ברייתא braisa is about unloading, and it's basically
saying our responsibility is to help the—if the Jew's donkey is being
crushed, help, but if it's a non-Jew's, you don't have to worry
about it. So clearly צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is not
דאורייתא d'Oraisa in this ברייתא. braisa. So what are we going to
do about it? אלא הא מני רבי יוסי הגלילי היא, דאמר צער
בעלי חיים לאו דאורייתא. Ella ha mani Rabbi Yosei ha-Gelili hi, d'amar
tza'ar ba'alei chayim lav d'Oraisa. Fine. If you back me into a
corner and you show me some tannaic source, I can always say
it's רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yosei ha-Gelili. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei
ha-Gelili says that if the owner overloaded it, you don't have a
responsibility. So it's clear that for רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yosei ha-Gelili,
צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is not the operative principle. So
that's how we'll explain a ברייתא braisa that does not work with
our philosophy, with our approach. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
goes on. תא
שמע, Ta shema, come in here. אוהב לפרוק ושונא לטעון. Ohev lifrok
v'sonei liton. If you have in front of you two people—because the
פסוקים pesukim talk also about is it חמור שונאך chamor soneicha or
not? So the donkey of your neighbor or the donkey of the
one who you hate? So why does it say you hate? Because
there's a special מצוה mitzvah to help somebody you hate to conquer
over your יצר הרע yeitzer hara in order and do the right
thing. So let's say you have to choose between unloading the donkey
of somebody you have a good relationship with and reloading it for
a different donkey of somebody that you hate. Which one takes precedence?
מצוה בשונא כדי לכוף את יצרו. Mitzvah b'sonei k'dei lachof es yitzro.
The מצוה mitzvah is to— Reload the one of the person you
hate because that will subjugate your יצר, yetzer, it'll help you maybe
transcend this enmity between you. ואי סלקא דעתך, Ve'isalka da'atakh, so the
גמרא, Gemara, that's all very nice if this is about interpersonal. But
if it's about the animal, how does that fit into the calculus?
ואי סלקא דעתך צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא הא עדיפא, Ve'isalka da'atakh tza'ar
ba'alei chayim de'oraita ha adifa, so but if the Gemara
says but if it's about the suffering of the animal, that should
trump. So the Gemara says no, אפילו הכי כדי לכוף את יצרו
עדיף. Afilu hakhi kedei lakhof et yitzro adif. No, even if the
obligation of the mitzvah or central part of it is concerned with
the animal, just because צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is דאורייתא
de'oraita doesn't mean that there aren't other דאורייתא de'oraita principles. And trying
to transcend, you know, there's a מצוה mitzvah of אהבת ישראל ahavat
Yisrael and לא תשנא את אחיך בלבבך. lo tisna et achikha bilvavekha.
So other principles can transcend even if it's not the central operative
principle of what this mitzvah is about. Okay, or can trump. Okay,
תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. שונא שאמרו שונא ישראל ולא
שונא עובד כוכבים. Sonei she'amru sonei Yisrael velo sonei oved kokhavim. When
it says that, you know, you have to return an animal, unload
the animal of חמור שונאך chamor sone'akha of the person you hate,
that's talking about if it's of a Jew that you have hatred
with, but not a non-Jew. A non-Jew you don't have an obligation
to unload the animal. So again it seems like we're not concerned
about צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. אי אמרת צער בעלי חיים
דאורייתא מה לי שונא ישראל מה לי שונא עובד כוכבים? Ei amrat
tza'ar ba'alei chayim de'oraita mah li sonei Yisrael mah li sonei oved
kokhavim? Why should you make a distinction between whether the animal is
owned by a Jew or non-Jew? The poor animal is suffering. So
the Gemara says no, מי סברת שונא דקרא קאמר? Mi savrat sonei
dekra ka'amar? We're not talking about where the פסוק pasuk says חמור
שונאך chamor sone'akha and the מצוה mitzvah of unloading. No, שונא דמתניתין
קאמר. sonei dematnitin ka'amar. We're talking about our Mishnah that says this
Baraita or
you know or דמתניתין, dematnitin, the Baraita we just quoted a second
ago that if you have to choose between unloading the donkey of
somebody you love or reloading one of hate, you do the one
of the person you hate. And the Gemara says but that's only
if it's between Jews because there's some mitzvah to love Jews and
to transcend hatred and so on. Okay, but that's not going back
to the פסוקים. pesukim. All right, תא שמע, Ta shema, come in
here. Top of ל"ג עמוד
א'. Lamed Gimmel Amud Aleph. רובץ ולא רבצן. Rovetz velo ravtzan. It
says the animal is crouching under its load but not one that
habitually crouches. רובץ ולא עומד תחת משאו. Rovetz velo omed tachat masa'o.
Only if it's actually now sort of crouching, but not if it's
struggling but still stands. ולא מפורק, Velo mefurak, and not something that
also
is unloaded that, you know, you don't then you don't have to
reload it up. So the Gemara's going to ask what does that
mean? You do have to reload it up. But okay, תחת משאו,
Tachat masa'o, under its burden. משוי שיכול לעמוד בו. Masui sheyakhol la'amod
bo. Only a burden that it should, you know, is appropriate for.
If it's overburdened, the owner is negligent, you don't have responsibility. ואי
אמרת צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא מה לי רובץ מה לי רבצן ומה
לי עומד? Ve'ei amrat tza'ar ba'alei chayim de'oraita mah li rovetz mah
li ravtzan umah li omed? If the concern is about the animal,
not about the owner and the owner's negligence or whatever, what do
I care if it habitually crouches or it, you know, or if
it stands or if it's crouching? The animal is struggling and suffering.
So none of those factors should matter. So the Gemara says no,
הא מני רבי יוסי הגלילי היא דאמר צער בעלי חיים דרבנן. Ha
manni Rabbi Yosei HaGelili hi de'amar tza'ar ba'alei chayim derabbanan. Yeah, this
Baraita here is all Rabbi Yosei HaGelili that makes all these exceptions
and we know that he thinks that צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei
chayim is only דרבנן, derabbanan, is not דאורייתא. de'oraita. הכי נמי מסתברא,
Hakhi nami mistabra, that makes sense said the Gemara, דקתני תחת משאו
משוי שיכול לעמוד בו. dekatani tachat masa'o masui sheyakhol la'amod bo. Because
the end of that is very clear. That's exactly Rabbi Yosei HaGelili.
Only if it has an appropriate burden. If the owner gave it
an
overburdened it, that you're not responsible. מאן שמעת ליה דאית ליה האי
סברא רבי יוסי הגלילי שמע מינה. Man shamat leh d'it leh hai
sevara Rabbi Yosei HaGelili shema mina. It's who holds that Rabbi Yosei
HaGelili clearly, so yes this whole Baraita is
not concerned about the suffering of the animal. Okay, מי מצית מוקמת
לה כרבי יוסי הגלילי והקתני סיפא תחת משאו ולא מפורק? Mi matzit
mokmat lah k'Rabbi Yosei HaGelili vehakatani seifa tachat masa'o velo mefurak? But
we also have the Baraita also says only under its burden and
not if it's already unloaded. Now what does that even mean? So
מאי לא מפורק? Mai lo mefurak? What does that mean? אילימא לא
מפורק כלל והכתיב הקם תקים עמו? Ilima lo mefurak klal vehaktiv hakeim
takim imo? If it's unloaded you have no
obligation, but it's written you do have an obligation to reload it.
אלא פשיטא, Ela peshita, the only way it's the only thing it
could mean when it's excluding מפורק: mefurak: לא מפורק בחנם אלא בשכר.
Lo mefurak bechinam ela besakhar. That if it's unloaded, then you don't
have to do it for free reloading it. The reloading you can
actually charge. So the Gemara says: מאן שמעת ליה דאית ליה האי
סברא רבנן? Man shamat leh d'it leh hai sevara Rabbanan? What that
is a debate in the Mishnah about רבנן Rabbanan and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and it's the Rabbis who hold that position that at
the reloading you can actually charge. So how can you say that
the Baraita is Rabbi Yosei HaGelili? Clearly it is the רבנן. Rabbanan.
All right, so now the Gemara is going to give an obvious
answer. So the Gemara says like this, the Gemara says: לעולם רבי
יוסי הגלילי הוא ובהא סבר לה כרבנן. Le'olam Rabbi Yosei HaGelili hu
uveha savar lah keRabbanan. These are unrelated debates. The Rabbis, you know,
of the Mishnah say this distinction between charging for reloading. Rabbi Yosei
HaGelili doesn't say his opinion about that. So
Rabbi Yosei HaGelili who says צער בעלי חיים לאו דאורייתא, tza'ar ba'alei
chayim lav de'oraita, תחת משאו משוי. tachat masa'o masui. Now again, maybe
it's less likely to think that given it's not about צער בעלי
חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim, but even so you can understand that there's
helping somebody when the animal's collapsing is a bigger imperative than helping
them reloading. So even if he's not holding that the principle of
צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is what's operative, he can still
hold of a difference between פריקה prikah and טעינה. te'inah. Okay, תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So now we are done with this debate, is
צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim דאורייתא, d'Oraita, yes or no? The
evidence actually seemed more to weigh in the principle of no, or
at least that's not the operative principle here by פריקה prikah and
טעינה, te'inah, but it went back and forth without a conclusion. Elsewhere
the גמרא Gemara seems to conclude that צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei
chayim is דאורייתא. d'Oraita. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. כי
תראה, ki tir'eh, you could even from a distance, if you see
the, you know, the donkey. So maybe even if it's at a
long distance, like you know you could see it like five miles
away, it's a clear day, it's flat land, so do you have
to run over and help? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, כי תפגע, ki
tifga, if you encounter, which means that you really bump into it.
אי כי תפגע, i ki tifga, יכול פגיעה ממש, yachol pegi'ah mamash,
ממש mamash you have to like bang into it, like even at
it has to be at no distance? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, כי
תראה, ki tir'eh, when you see. So what's the middle? So it's
seeing, not directly being there, but also not being very far away,
seeing that's close enough to say you've encountered it. So איזהו ראייה
שיש בה פגיעה? eizehu re'iyah she-yesh bah pegi'ah? What would that be?
שיערו חכמים אחד משבעה ומחצה במיל. Shi'aru chachamim echad mi-shiv'ah u-mechtzah be-mil.
It is one out of seven and a half, meaning 2/15th of
a מיל. mil. A מיל mil is 2,000
אמה, ammah, so 2/15th of that is, oh I did this math,
it's about if I remember correctly about 266 אמה, ammah, which is
about 350 feet give or take. Okay, like 100 yards. All right,
no, is that right? Yeah, about 100 yards. What's 100 yards? That's
the length of a football field, right? Okay, so that's actually not
a, that's not such a small distance. Okay,
וזהו ריס, ve-zehu ris, and that's a ריס, ris, that length is
called a ריס. ris. תנא ומדדה עמו עד פרסה. Tana: u-medado imo
ad parsah. After you reload it, you accompany the owner for a
פרסה. parsah. פרסה Parsah is four מיל. mil. So that's 8,000 אמה.
ammah. So that's about 12,000 feet. Okay, so what is that?
12,000 feet, that's a lot. Okay, so you have to walk with
the owner for a פרסה parsah to make sure the animal doesn't
recollapse. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, וזהו, ve-zehu, אמר רבה
בר בר חנה ונוטל שכר. Amar Rabbah bar bar Channah: u-notel sachar.
To go all that distance, you know, you can actually charge. That's
actually quite making quite a demand to be walking with him for
that long. The גמרא Gemara assumes that it takes about 18 minutes
to walk a מיל, mil, so you're walking with him that's, you
know, you're walking with him for like 72 minutes. That's quite significant.
Okay, next משנה. Mishnah. Now that is done with פריקה prikah and
טעינה, te'inah, one last משנה Mishnah about אבידה. avedah.
אבידתו ואבידת אביו אבידתו קודמת, Avedato va-avedat aviv, avedato kodemet, this is
a famous משנה. Mishnah. If you have to choose between, you know,
returning your own אבידה, avedah, you know, running after your own אבידה
avedah or running after your father's, or a similar case would be
if you have to give up, you know, earnings in order to
get your father's אבידה avedah and it would cost, so you're going
to be losing out, right? We had that type of אבידה avedah
before as well. Who, if you have to choose between the two
of them, אבידתו קודמת. avedato kodemet. Yours comes first. Because even when
it comes to your father, you know, the basic principle is in
Jewish ethics is that our ethical responsibility is stronger to those that
are closer to us. You know, those of your city versus those
of another city, your family versus those of the city. So your
first obligation is to yourself. So actually, you know, that yours comes
before your father's. אבידתו ואבידת רבו שלו קודמת, Avedato va-avedat rabbo, shelo
kodemet, and it comes before your רבי Rebbi also. אבידת אביו ואבידת
רבו, עכשיו, Avedat aviv va-avedat rabbo, achshav, now if you have to
choose between running after your father's אבידה avedah or your רבי's Rebbi
אבידה, avedah, של רבו קודמת. shel rabbo kodemet. Your רבי Rebbi comes
first. שאביו הביאו לעולם הזה ורבו שלמדו חכמה מביאו לחיי העולם הבא.
She-aviv hevi'o la-olam ha-zeh, ve-rabbo she-limdo chochmah mevi'o le-chayei ha-olam ha-ba. Your
father brings you into this world, but your רבי Rebbi who teaches
you חכמה, chochmah, which is a question of what constitutes a רבי,
Rebbi, which we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, that person, you know,
sets you on your path for life and your religious path, and
therefore that actually gives even greater precedence. You know, so this is
actually people sometimes get very upset. The rabbis are writing the rules
and they've decided, you know, that the רבי Rebbi is more important
than the father.
But, you know, and that's a whole discussion also comparing the מצווה
mitzvah of כיבוד אב kibbud av and כיבוד רב kibbud rav and
so on. But, you know, obviously they, yeah, they are committed to
this idea. It's not about their own personal כבוד, kavod, but they
are committed to the idea that the greatest thing you can do
in life is learn תורה Torah and pursue your religious pursuits and
ultimately that's עולם הבא olam ha-ba and that's your eternal soul. So
I don't think that this is about them serving themselves, but I
do think it's about that this is very much their central value
system. Okay, so that takes precedence.
Now, ואם אביו חכם, של אביו קודמת. ve-im aviv chacham, shel aviv
kodemet. But if your father is a חכם, chacham, then your father
comes first. It's interesting, it does not sound... that your father has
to have taught you as much as your רבי, rebbe, but your
father also deserves כבוד kavod because he also is a חכם chacham
even if your רבי rebbe is a greater חכם. chacham. Does your
father have to have taught you something, have to have helped your
religious education? Yeah, it leaves it very ambiguous, but it does seem
that once your father's in the פרשה, parsha, he's going to get
precedence over your רבי. rebbe. היה אביו ורבו נושאים משאוי, haya aviv
v'rabo nosim masoy, so same הלכה halacha if they're both carrying a
burden, and assuming that the idea of פריקה וטעינה, prika u-teina, we
saw this a little bit before as well, would similarly apply if
the person is carrying the burden. מניח את של רבו ואחר כך
מניח את של אביו. maniach es shel rabo v'achar kach maniach es
shel aviv. First you help your רבי rebbe get unloaded his burden
and then your father. היה אביו ורבו בבית השבי, haya aviv v'rabo
b'veis ha-shavi, if they're both in prison, in captivity, obviously very poignant
nowadays, פודה את רבו ואחר כך פודה את אביו. podeh es rabo
v'achar kach podeh es aviv. Your first obligation is to your רבי
rebbe again. Given all the תורה'ס Torah's clarity about, you know, being
so emphasizing כבד את אביך ואת אמך Kabeid es avicha v'es imecha
and כבוד הרב kevod ha-rav is learned out like הדר פני זקן,
hadar p'nei zaken, nearly not nearly as strong of a sense, and
the strong ties of family, you know, this is a pretty challenging,
I would say, for our normal ways we think of the bonds
of relationship, you know, what the משנה mishna is saying. ואם אביו
חכם, v'im aviv chacham, but again if the father is a חכם,
chacham, פודה את אביו ואחר כך פודה את רבו, podeh es aviv
v'achar kach podeh es rabo, then he takes precedence. And again, it
seems even if he is not at the level of the רבי,
rebbe, even if he didn't teach as much as the רבי, rebbe,
once he's in the
פרשה parsha of somebody who represents תורה, Torah, then the father automatically
takes precedence. Let's see the גמרא. gemara. מנא הני מילי, mena hanei
mili, where did you get this idea from that yours comes first?
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אמר קרא אפס כי לא יהיה בך
אביון, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav amar kra efes ki lo yihiyeh
becha evyon, however there should not be in you a poor person,
שלך קודם לשל כל אדם. shelcha kodem l'shel kol adam. You have
to first ensure that you are coming, you know, first, making sure
you don't become poor. Right? It's חייך וחיי אחיך. chayecha v'chayei achicha.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב כל המקיים בעצמו כך סוף בא לידי
כך. v'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav kol ha-mekayem b'atzmo kach sof ba
l'yedei kach. Even though that's true that you have a right to
take your own needs first, if that's what you're always focused on,
making sure that your needs are met, never transcending your needs for
somebody else, so if you're always insisting on that, in the end
you will become poor. You know, yeah, so on the one hand,
yes, your primary obligation is to yourself, and on the other hand,
you should actually try to, you know, when possible, try to transcend
that and do for others. Okay. היה אביו ורבו נושאים משאוי. haya
aviv v'rabo nosim masoy. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, רבו שאמרו רבו שלמדו
חכמה ולא רבו שלמדו מקרא ומשנה דברי רבי מאיר. rabo she-amru rabo
she-limdo chochma v'lo rabo she-limdo mikra u-mishna divrei Rabbi Meir. Who constitutes
this רבי rebbe that comes before your father? So the first position
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is that it's the one who teaches
you חכמה, chochma, you know, really set you, gave you your primary
education and also, not primary in terms of ABCs,
like the high-level תורה Torah education. So חכמה chochma here means sort
of גמרא, gemara, analysis, not just memorization of משנה mishna and פסוקים.
p'sukim. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי יהודה אומר כל
שרוב חכמתו הימנו. Rabbi Yehuda omer kol she-rov chochmato heimenu. Only one
רבי rebbe is זוכה zocheh to this. It's not anybody who teaches
you גמרא, gemara, so on the one hand it's more limiting, but
it's also more expansive. Not everybody's going to learn גמרא. gemara. So
if, so as you know,
if you've only learned מקרא mikra and most of your תורה Torah
knowledge comes from him, that's your רבי. rebbe. If you've only learned
משנה, mishna, that's your רבי. rebbe. So it's a nice, it's an
interesting debate. You know, this is both more subjective, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir only gives valuing to like גמרא, gemara, and רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi
Yehuda's more subjective for the person but also it's your one main
רבי, rebbe, would says רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי אומר אפילו
לא האיר עיניו אלא במשנה אחת זו היא רבו. Rabbi Yose omer
afilu lo heir einav ela b'mishna achas zu hi rabo. Even if
he only lit your eyes up with one משנה, mishna, anybody that
teaches you anything, even gives you one insight is a רבי. rebbe.
Now, does that mean a רבי rebbe for כבוד, kavod, which we'll
see in a minute, or does this, what's the context here? Is
it to give כבוד kavod or is it takes precedence over your
father? There's obviously a big difference here. So let's take a look
as the גמרא gemara continues. Okay, אמר רבא כגון רב סחורה
דאסברן זוהמא ליסטרון, amar Rava k'gon Rav Schora d'asbran zuhama listron, like
רב סחורה Rav Schora דאסברן זוהמא ליסטרון. d'asbran zuhama listron.
He explained to me what this meaning of זוהמא ליסטרון zuhama listron
in כלים Keilim was about a type of a spoon that you
would use to remove the froth over a of a pot. So
he told me, you know, it's like כלים Keilim is very technical
about practical objects and he explained to me what this spoon was.
So that would be somebody that opened up my eyes in one
משנה. mishna. שמואל קרע מאני עליה דההוא מרבנן. Shmuel kra mani alei
d'hahu me-rabanan. שמואל Shmuel did קריעה kriah for one of the rabbis,
meaning one of the rabbinical students, like not a major תלמיד חכם,
talmid chacham, just one of the rabbinical students, דאסבריה אחד יורד לאמת
השחי ואחד פותח כיון, d'asbrei echad yored l'amas ha-shachi v'echad poseiach kivan,
about how when the כהנים kohanim would go to open up the
doors to the היכל, Heichal, you have this phrase, one would go
down to the to where his armpit was, he would stretch it
in to his armpit and then he would open the other door
directly. So it's not exactly clear like visually what is it describing?
He explained that to me, so he would, you know, he did
קריעה kriah if that person, when that person would die, because that
person he would treat as one of of his רבנים, rebbeim, somebody
who enlightened him in that one thing. So this is about showing
honor, right, but it is not necessarily giving them precedence over your
father. So let's keep on going. Okay. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim שבבבל she'be'Bavel עומדים זה מפני זה omdim zeh mi'pnei
zeh וקורעים זה על זה. v'kori'im zeh al zeh.
So the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim in בבל, Bavel, you know, they're
all learning with one another, they're colleagues. So each one is everybody
else's רבי. rebbe. So when one of them walks in the room,
they stand, you know, the other one walks in the room, they
stand. And if one of them dies, God forbid, you do קריעה.
kriah. Okay.
And that's a type of a קריעה kriah רש״י Rashi points out
that you do for a תלמיד talmid does קריעה kriah for a
רבי rebbe that you would never sew it up afterwards, like, you
know, קריעה kriah for parents. So they treated one, everybody treated everybody
else as a רבי. rebbe. That's in terms of honor. ולענין אבידה
במקום אביו אינו חוזר אלא לרבו מובהק. U'le'inyan aveida bi'mkom aviv eino
chozer ela l'rabo muvhak.
So that's a very nice qualification. All of this is all very
nice, but when it comes to the issue of who's going to
take precedence over your father, only your רבו מובהק, rabo muvhak, only
your main רבי. rebbe. So sounds like a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
approach, you know, and does it mean whatever subjectively is the חכמה
chochma you know? Anyway, but there's only one person who takes precedence
and that's רבו מובהק. rabo muvhak. Okay.
Where are we? קבעי מיניה רב חסדא מרב הונא. K'ba'ei minei Rav
Chisda me'Rav Huna. רב חסדא Rav Chisda asked רב הונא. Rav Huna.
תלמיד וצריך לו רבו מאי? Talmid v'tzarich lo rabo mai?
Let's say you have a תלמיד talmid that the רבי rebbe like
relies on the תלמיד, talmid, you know, the תלמיד talmid has a
lot of stuff memorized and the רבי rebbe says remind me, you
know, what's that משנה mishna over there or something. So they're in
this sort of symbiotic relationship. So he said, you know, would that
תלמיד, talmid, even though he, you know, before we talked about colleagues,
you know, what would the רבי's rebbe relationship be to that תלמיד?
talmid? Would he, I don't know, it's asking the question about החזרת
אבידה hachazarat aveida but maybe about standing or doing קריעה, kriah, you
know, like the discussion before.
So let's take a look at what he answered. אמר ליה, Amar
lei,
so רב הונא Rav Huna said to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, חסדא
חסדא לא צריכנא לך. Chisda Chisda la tzerichna lach. חסדא חסדא, Chisda
Chisda,
I don't need you, I don't rely on you. את צריכת לי,
At tzerichat li, you need me. He thought that רב חסדא Rav
Chisda was referring to himself and he was offended. ארבעין שנין איקפד
אהדדי. Arba'in shanin ikpad ahadadei. For 40 years they had this, you
know, they held this against one another. ולא עיילי לגבי הדדי. V'lo
ayilei l'gabei ahadadei.
And they did not, you know, they couldn't talk to one another.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda felt I wasn't talking about myself, I can't
believe you thought that about me, that I was talking about myself,
you know, and רב הונא Rav Huna felt I can't believe he
thought that I needed him, or maybe he felt guilty that, you
know, that he had suspected him of that.
Okay. יתיב רב חסדא ארבעין תעניתא משום דחלש דעתיה דרב הונא. Yativ
Rav Chisda arba'in ta'anita mishum d'chalash da'ateih d'Rav Huna. So רב חסדא
Rav Chisda sat 40 תעניות ta'aniyot
that he said something that let, you know, that led רב הונא
Rav Huna be despondent, you know, even if he didn't mean it,
nevertheless, his question made רב הונא Rav Huna think that he thought
that, you know, that he thought that רב הונא Rav Huna needed
him, you know, relied on him. יתיב רב הונא ארבעין תעניתא משום
דחשדיה לרב חסדא. Yativ Rav Huna arba'in ta'anita mishum d'chashdiyeh l'Rav Chisda.
So רב הונא Rav Huna sat 40 תעניות ta'anitas that he thought
that רב חסדא Rav Chisda was talking about himself. So it's very
funny, everybody feels guilty and even though they feel guilty, they're still
angry at one another. It's like what good does guilt do? You
know, guilt is like you beat yourself up and you think it's
going to, like it's completely counterproductive. They should feel less guilty and
they should apologize and move on, you know? But it's like they're
both offended and guilty.
Okay. איתמר, Itmar, it was taught. רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי
יוחנן הלכה כרבי יהודה. Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha
k'Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which is also
seemed before that we go by like your main רבי. rebbe. רב
אחא בר רב הונא אמר רב ששת הלכה כרבי יוסי. Rav Acha
bar Rav Huna amar Rav Sheshet halacha k'Rabbi Yosi. No, we rule
like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that says even האיר עיניו במשנה אחת.
he'ir einav be'mishna achat. Again, does it mean precedence over your father
or does it mean for כבוד? kavod? It sounds like it means
precedence over your father, that's our context. ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי
והאמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה ותנן רבו שלמדו חכמה? U'mi amar
Rabbi Yochanan hachi v'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha k'stam mishna u'tnan rabo she'limdo
chochma? Now the גמרא Gemara makes it clear we're talking about precedence
over your father. How could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say we go
by רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which is, you know, which is like
your רבו מובהק? rabo muvhak? רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan general principle is
you go by the סתם משנה. stam mishna. And the סתם משנה
stam mishna says the רבי rebbe who taught you חכמה. chochma. חכמה
Chochma sounds like a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir word, like גמרא Gemara
and like it's not like רבו מובהק. rabo muvhak. ותנן רבו שלמדו
חכמה. U'tnan rabo she'limdo chochma. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מאי
חכמה רוב חכמתו. mai chochma rov chochmato.
No, the משנה mishna could be רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. It doesn't
mean דוקא davka גמרא, Gemara, and it doesn't and it means the
one you got most of your education from. All right. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan. Now because this obviously has created some priorities here between
משנה mishna and גמרא Gemara and so on, we're going to say
explicitly what was implicit until now. העוסקים במקרא מדה ואינה מדה. Ha'oskim
be'mikra mida v'eina mida. Those who learn Torah, it's a value, but
it's not of the greatest value. במשנה מדה ונוטלין עליה שכר. Be'mishna
mida v'notlin aleha schar. משנה Mishna is already something that you get
reward for because It's ultimately leading into the
learning of גמרא, Gemara, but גמרא אין לך מדה גדולה מזו, Gemara
ein lach middah gedolah mizu, but if you learn גמרא, Gemara, you
have nothing is greater than this level.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is, hold on a second, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues and the גמרא Gemara says like this.
גמרא Gemara says תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis
taught, oh
just sorry, אין לך מדה גדולה מזו, לעולם הוי רץ למשנה יותר
מן הגמרא, Ein lach middah gedolah mizu, leolam havei ratz lamishnah yoter
min hagemara, but you should always run to learn משנה Mishnah more
than גמרא. Gemara. So, huh? Didn’t you just say גמרא Gemara was
more important? הגופא קשיא, Hagufa kashya, that’s internally contradictory. אמרת בגמרא אין
לך מדה גדולה מזו, Amarta begemara ein lach middah gedolah mizu, והדר
אמרת לעולם הוי רץ למשנה יותר מן הגמרא. Vehadar amarta leolam havei
ratz lamishnah yoter min hagemara. First you said nothing better than גמרא
Gemara and then you said you should always run to משנה Mishnah
before גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so says רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, בימי רבי נשנית משנה זו, Bimei Rebbe nishneit mishnah
zu, this was taught in the time of רבי, Rebbe, you know,
when רבי Rebbe was sort of editing and organizing all the משניות.
Mishnayot. שבקו כולי עלמא מתניתין ואזלו בתר גמרא. Shavku kulei alma matnitin
veazlu batar gemara.
So everybody, so רש"י Rashi explains that what this means is that
in the time of, that before רבי, Rebbe, you had a lot
of people that just memorized משניות, Mishnayot, but there was no attempt
to try to understand them more deeply, to try to deal with
contradictory משניות, Mishnayot, different traditions. Everybody had the משניות Mishnayot that their
רבי Rebbe taught them. And what רבי Rebbe did in order to
put together the משנה Mishnah is he gathered everybody
together, he discussed and figured out what was behind the משניות, Mishnayot,
what was going on, what was the meaning and so on, and
through that they determined which were the משניות Mishnayot that were the
primary ones and the ones that should be included in the משנה,
Mishnah, which one more secondary and in the ברייתא, Braita, which were
the ones that we should be פוסק-ing pasken the הלכה halacha like
and make it a סתם משנה. stam mishnah. So because רבי Rebbe
turned all of this rote memorization of משנה Mishnah and contradictory traditions
into an organized and getting into the depth of it and so
on, he wanted to really prioritize the learning of גמרא Gemara and
he said גמרא אין לך מדה גדולה מזו. Gemara ein lach middah
gedolah mizu. Okay, but what happened? שבקו כולי עלמא מתניתין ואזלו בתר
גמרא. Shavku kulei alma matnitin veazlu batar gemara. So then everybody completely
abandoned משנה Mishnah and everybody was just learning גמרא. Gemara. You know,
people love doing סברא, svara, but you can’t do it. It’s another
way the גמרא Gemara sometimes asks, what’s more important, the person with
analytical skills or the person with a storehouse of knowledge? You can’t
apply your analysis if you’re ignorant of the facts. So you got
to figure out the right balance. So הדר דרש להו לעולם הוי
רץ למשנה יותר מן הגמרא. Hadar darash lehu leolam havei ratz lamishnah
yoter min hagemara. And then he said, no, no, no, go to
משנה Mishnah more than גמרא Gemara in order to recalibrate the focus.
Okay, but ultimately, you got to know the משנה, Mishnah, you got
to know the facts. גמרא Gemara is the analysis and that leads
to knowing הלכה, halacha, and presumably that’s why it’s more important than
פסוקים, psukim, because פסוקים psukim don’t lead to actual הלכה. halacha. That
seems to be the distinction. Of course, the learning of גמרא Gemara
is not just הלכה, halacha, you learn קדשים, Kodashim, you learn טהרות.
Taharot. Obviously, some of it could also be how much it’s seen
to be intellectually demanding and challenging and so on, intense. But also,
it
was there was a pushback about this. The רשב"ם Rashbam in his
הקדמה hakdamah to his commentary on the תורה Torah says because חז"ל
Chazal said if you learn מקרא mikra it’s מדה ואינה מדה, middah
veeinah middah, people don’t learn תנ"ך Tanakh so much and they’re really
ignorant of it and you have to, it’s the basis of our
tradition. Also, it was a big thing in the Middle Ages because
the Christians were using it against the Jews. So, and I think
for a lot of people nowadays, גמרא Gemara can be too legalistic.
You need to learn פסוקים, psukim, תנ"ך, Tanakh, מחשבה machshava to give
you a little bit of like the השקפה hashkafa and a little
bit of like the religious sensibility. So it’s all about finding the
right balance, but clearly the גמרא's Gemara bias was towards the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, מאי דריש? Mai darish? What did he, how did he
דרשן darshen this to say that the גמרא Gemara is most important?
כדדרש רבי יהודה בר אלעאי, Kiddarash Rabbi Yehudah bar Ila'i, מאי דכתיב,
mai dicheitiv, what’s meant by הגד לעמי פשעם ולבית יעקב חטאתם, hagged
leammi pisham uleveit Yaakov chattatam, tell my people their sin and to
בית יעקב Beit Yaakov their iniquity. So הגד לעמי פשעם, Hagged leammi
pisham, so פשע pesha is like intentional sin. אלו תלמידי חכמים ששגגות
נעשות להם כזדונות. Elu talmidei chachamim sheshegagot naasot lahem kizedonot.
That’s תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim because if they make an error in
ruling, God’s going to treat it like it’s a פשע, pesha, like
it’s an intentional sin because they’ve been negligent in their study and
their responsibility is to know the הלכה halacha and פוסק pasken correctly.
So if it’s עמי, ammi, meaning my favored ones, because the תלמידי
חכמים, talmidei chachamim, if they sin, it’s always going to be treated
as a פשע. pesha. Okay, and that’s why you really have to
learn גמרא Gemara very, very seriously, because God’s going to really hold
you accountable. ולבית יעקב חטאתם, Uleveit Yaakov chattatam, and בית יעקב Beit
Yaakov their חטא, chet, and חטא chet is understood as an unintentional
sin. אלו עמי הארץ שזדונות נעשות להם כשגגות. Elu ammei haaretz shezedonot
naasot lahem kishigagot. That is the עמי הארץ ammei haaretz that even
when they do intentionally sin, it’s most of the time, it has
a lot to do with ignorance rather than like real intention.
Therefore. but okay, so the second part is not relevant to
the דרש drash about גמרא, Gemara, but the first part is, as
תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, you have a high responsibility. You'd better really
know the analysis. Okay, והיינו דתנן, V'hainu d'tenan, רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi
Yehuda omer, הוי זהיר בתלמוד, Havei zahir b'talmud, you should be very
careful in your learning of גמרא, Gemara, ששגגת תלמוד עולה זדון, Sheshiggas
talmud ola l'zadon, if you make an error, you're going to be
treated as a willful sin. דרש רבי יהודה בר אלעאי, Darash Rebbi
Yehuda bar Elai, מאי דכתיב, mai d'ksiv, what's meant by the פסוק,
pasuk,
שמעו דבר ה' החרדים אל דברו, Shimu devar Hashem hacharedim el devaro,
listen to the word of God those who are tremble, that's the
word חרדי charedi over his word. אלו תלמידי חכמים, Elu talmidei chachamim,
these are the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and they presumably tremble because
a mistake is held, they're really held to account. Okay,
אמרו אחיכם, Amru achichem, say your brothers, אלו בעלי מקרא, elu baalei
mikra, these are the people that learn תורה, Torah, they learn פסוקים,
psukim, they're not, yeah, they're your brothers, they're in the same, they're
committed to learning but they're not the major תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim.
שונאיכם, Soneichem, those who hate you, אלו בעלי משנה, elu baalei mishna,
people who learn משנה. mishna. And why do they hate you? We
hadn't seen this before, but it's basically because people who learn משנה
mishna think they know הלכה, halacha, think they know תורה שבעל פה,
Torah she'be'al peh, they פסקן הלכה, pasken halacha, and they actually פסקן
pasken it incorrectly. And the גמרא Gemara is very critical of them
and they say people that just know משנה mishna are מבלי עולם,
mavlai olam, they destroy the world. So there's a lot
of the closer somebody is to you, the more sometimes hatred that
there can be between them. So the people who learn פסוקים, psukim,
we all like each other, we're dealing with different things. People who
learn משנה, mishna, that's
שונאיכם, soneichem, אלו בעלי משנה. elu baalei mishna. מנדיכם, Menadeichem, those that
put you into נידוי, niddui, like excommunication or רש"י Rashi says treat
you like
people cast out. אלו עמי הארץ, Elu amei ha'aretz, those are the
עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz because we also know there was a lot
of enmity between חז"ל Chazal and the עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz. So
these are, there are a lot of tensions within the society here.
But שמא תאמר פסק סברם ובטל סיכויים, Shema tomar pasak sivram u'batel
sikkuyam, but lest you say that just because that there's these different
groups and there's enmity between it, lest you say that means that
somehow their hope and their value has been over. So lest you
say their hope is over and their chances are done, תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, ונראה בשמחתכם, V'nira b'simchaschem, you will see in their
rejoicing in the end even with these sort of, you're all still
brothers even with all of these fights. שמא תאמר ישראל יבושו, Shema
tomar Yisrael yevoshu, maybe it means the פסוק pasuk that you will
be embarrassed because of these fights, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, והם יבושו,
V'hem yevoshu, עובדי כוכבים יבושו וישראל ישמחו. Ovdei kochavim yevoshu v'Yisrael yismechu.
All right, so again that will be for the non-Jews, not for
the Jews, maybe echoing back some of the lack of concern of
the non-Jews that we had also by the case of the פריקת
וטעינה. prika u'teina. הדרן עלך אלו מציאות. Hadran alach elu metzios. All
right, we're going to do a, that was the end of the
first two פרקים prakim which had to do with finding lost objects.
The first about interesting cases of finding lost objects, the second פרק
perek about the basic מצוה mitzvah of returning lost objects. Now we
are going to start the third פרק, perek, we're going to get
to the bottom and catch up. Okay, this now talks about moving
on from lost objects to entrusted objects, שומרים. shomrim. המפקיד אצל חברו
בהמה או כלים, Hamapkid etzel chaveiro beheima o keilim, somebody who entrusts
by his friend an animal or vessels, echoing the פסוקים psukim about
that, and you're שומר חנם, shomer chinam, you're watching them without being
paid, ונגנבו או שאבדו, v'nignevu o she'avdu, and then they were stolen
or lost, and a שומר חנם shomer chinam is exempt, he has
to swear that he was not negligent and that they were stolen
or lost, and then he gets off from paying. That's the הלכה.
halacha. So but he did not want to do that. שילם ולא
רצה לישבע, Shilem v'lo ratza lishava, he didn't want to swear and
instead he paid. Either he says I don't like taking
שבועות, shvuos, in general want to avoid שבועות shvuos which definitely was
a very big ethos amongst amongst Jews for many, many centuries. Or
maybe he just feels guilty, he feels I know that I did,
wasn't negligent, but I feel responsible, I'm going to pay, for whatever
the reason he agrees to pay and he's not interested in swearing.
So what happens? שהרי אמרו, Sheharei amru, שהרי אמרו שומר חנם נשבע
ויוצא, Sheharei amru shomer chinam nishba v'yotze, because he had the right
as we teach that a שומר חנם shomer chinam can swear and
be exempt, but he didn't want to. If he goes ahead and
does that, נמצא הגנב משלם תשלומי כפל, Nimtza haganav meshalem tashlumei khefel,
if the גנב ganav is found because it's a case of גניבה,
gneiva, it said אבידה aveida but whatever, that's parenthetical, it means גניבה.
gneiva. So if it's the burglar is found, he pays double.
טבח ומכר, Tavach u'machar, if it was a case of a sheep
or cow and he slaughtered it or sold it, משלם תשלומי ארבעה
וחמשה, meshalem tashlumei arba'a v'chamisha, he pays four or five. למי משלם,
L'mi meshalem,
so now who's he going to pay to? למי שהפיקדון אצלו, L'mi
she'hapikadon etzlo, the one who has been watching the object, meaning the
שומר, shomer, because the שומר shomer agreed to pay, if ever it
gets returned, well if it gets returned and it wasn't a גניבה,
gneiva, fine, he'll get it back, he paid now he's getting it
back. But if it gets returned by a גנב, ganav, he'll actually
get the benefit, he'll get the כפל khefel or the four and
five because he agreed to pay up front. when he could have
exempted himself. And we'll see in the גמרא Gemara different reasons, but
of course for this, the most obvious is that it just, it's
a good incentive, the owner is most interested, he doesn't want his
thing to get burgled so he might get כפל kefel or four
and five. He just wants his darn object back. And he doesn't
want the שומר shomer's שבועה, shevua, so therefore let's give שומרים shomrim
a little bit of an incentive to pay up even when they
could exempt themselves knowing that they might actually in some cases, at
least by גניבה, geneva, who knows, maybe they'll benefit from it. It'll
be better they can, if they can be promised that on the
off-chance they get that and it'll help the owner get restitution. That
seems to be what's going on here, but we'll see more of
this in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. למימרא נשבע ולא רצה לשלם. Lemeimra
nishba velo ratza leshalem.
However, if he took the oath and did not want to swear,
which is I'm sorry, and did not want to pay, which is
what you would expect. נמצא גנב משלם תשלומי כפל טבח ומכר משלם
תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. Nimtza gannav meshalem tashlumei kefel, tavach umachar meshalem tashlumei
arba'ah vachamishah. So again, if the גנב gannav is found, he pays
two or four and five. למי משלם לבעל הבית. Lemi meshalem leba'al
habayit. Now he pays it to the one who owns the object,
not the one who was watching the object, obviously. Okay, the real
חידוש chiddush is the first half of the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. למה לי למיתנא בהמה ולמה לי
למיתנא כלים. Lama li lemitna behemah velama li lemitna kelim. So first,
why did it both say בהמה behemah and כלים, kelim, which it
also says in the פסוקים. pesukim.
So it says, צריכי דאי תנא בהמה הוה אמינא בהמה הוא דמקני
ליה כפילא משום דנפיש טרחא לעיולה ולאפוקה. Tzrichi, dei tana behemah hava
amina behemah hu demakni leh kefila mishum denafish tircha le'iyula uleafoka.
Maybe this idea that he's going to get כפל, kefel, which is
a little bonus for the שומר, shomer, maybe that was only done
in a case where he was going to watch a בהמה, behemah,
where he's watching a בהמה behemah because he put in a lot
of effort, taking it out and grazing it and caring for it.
So that's a case he already put in all this effort, we'll
give him this little bonus of כפל kefel in this case. משום
דנפיש טרחא לעיולה ולאפוקה אבל כלים דלא נפיש טרחייהו אימא לא. Mishum
denafish tircha le'iyula uleafoka, aval kelim dela nafish tirchaihu eima lo. But
by כלים kelim where it's no effort, even if he agrees to
pay when he could have exempted himself, maybe we won't give him
כפל. kefel. So לא מקני ליה כפילא. lo makni leh kefila. ואי
תנא כלים, Ve'i tana kelim, and if it just start כלים, kelim,
הוה אמינא כלים הוא דמקני ליה כפילא משום דלא נפיש כפליהו. hava
amina kelim hu demakni leh kefila mishum dela nafish kiflaihu. If it
just had כלים, kelim, I would have said well maybe this idea,
this תקנה takanah or whatever the reason is we give him כפל,
kefel, we did it by vessels. Vessels are like, they're usually a
chair, a table, who knows what they are, they're not a lot
of money, so the owner isn't losing out a lot. The כפל
kefel is not a big amount. אבל בהמה דכי טבח ומכר משלם
תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. Aval behemah dechi tavach umachar meshalem tashlumei arba'ah vachamishah.
And also, I'm sorry, not only that, but also you never get
to four and five, you only get to כפל. kefel. אבל בהמה,
Aval behemah, but if you're talking about
an animal, דכי טבח ומכר משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה, dechi tavach umachar
meshalem tashlumei arba'ah vachamishah, by animal to pay off can be not
only two, it can be four or five. So אימא לא מקני
ליה כפילא, eima lo makni leh kefila, maybe they wouldn't have gone
so far to give כפל kefel in the case of an animal
or maybe they wouldn't have gone so far to give four and
five. So by בהמה behemah there's more of a reason the שומר
shomer might deserve a bonus if this happens, but also there's a
reason we would have thought at least not four and five, that's
a very very big payout. So it had to say both. צריכא,
Tzricha, it had to say both. Okay. It also should be mentioned,
the תורה Torah says both, and the תורה Torah says כלים kelim
by the case of a שומר חנם shomer chinam and בהמה behemah
by the case of a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, and the רשב"ם
Rashbam already points out exactly for this reason that since it's easier
to watch כלים, kelim, often people do it for free. בהמה Behemah
takes a lot of effort so often the default case is that
it's a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Let's just read the next few
lines as the גמרא Gemara starts to explain what the reason is
behind or what the mechanism is that the שומר shomer gets כפל.
kefel. מותקיף ליה רמי בר חמא. Maskif leh Rami bar Chama. Rami
bar Chama said and he asked: והא אין אדם מקנה דבר שלא
בא לעולם. Veha ein adam makne davar shelo ba la'olam. You used
the phrase in this discussion about בהמה behemah and כלים kelim מקני
ליה כפילא makni leh kefila which sounds like the owner, now I've
been saying it as חז"ל Chazal because that's how some ראשונים Rishonim
understand, but right now the גמרא Gemara's understanding it like the owner
is giving כפל kefel to the שומר. shomer. So רמי בר חמא
Rami bar Chama said, how can the owner be מקנה כפל makne
kefel to the give over the כפל kefel to the שומר shomer
when he agrees to pay? The כפל kefel doesn't exist yet, and
you can't give something that doesn't exist in the world, the כפל
kefel doesn't exist. ואפילו לרבי מאיר דאמר אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא
לעולם, Ve'afilu leRabbi Meir de'amar adam makne davar shelo ba la'olam, even
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who is attributed with this position that somebody,
a person can sell something that doesn't yet exist, הני מילי כגון
פירות דקלא דעבידי דאתו. hani mili kegon perot dikla de'avidi de'atu.
That's if you're going to sell somebody like the fruit off of
a tree then, if the tree hasn't borne the fruit yet, but
you pre-sell the fruit. But that's because it's natural that that fruit
will come into existence, so maybe it's like it's enough around,
virtually it's already here that you can sell. אבל הכא, Aval hacha,
but in our case, top of ל"ד ע"א, Lamed Dalet Amud Aleph,
מי יימר דמיגנבא? mi yeimar demignava?
Whoever says it's going to get stolen? Now it has been stolen,
but
okay, but the question is are we thinking you're being מקנה makne
the object originally when you gave him the object to watch, or
are you being מקנה makne the כפל kefel now when he agrees
to pay? When it says who knows it'll get stolen, it sounds
like the question is whether you were מקנה makne the object originally,
but let's focus on the כפל. kefel. Who knows it's going to
get stolen? ואם תמצי לומר דמגנב v'im timtzei lomar d'mignav ואפילו v'afilu
get stolen, מי יימר דמשתכח גנב, mi yeimar d'mishtakach ganav, who says
the גנב ganav will be found? ואם משתכח גנב, v'im mishtakach ganav,
if he's found, מי יימר דמשלם, mi yeimar d'mishaleim, how do you
know he's ever going to pay? דילמא מודי ומיפטר, dilma modei u'miftar,
maybe he'll just admit it and get off the hook. So, it
is so doubtful and speculative, how the heck can the owner be
מקנה makne the כפל? kefel? It doesn't exist yet, it's not considered
present, it's not even anticipated, and therefore there's no way if we
are making it that the owner is מקנה makne the כפל kefel
that he could be seen as doing this. So we will pick
up tomorrow at the beginning of למד דלת lamed daled to see
רבא's Rava answer to this question.